hi my name is Johnny and I'll be taking
you through the EEG from signal
formation to its clinical applications
in helping us understand epilepsy so the
first question you might ask is what is
an EEG EEG stands for
electroencephalogram which as you can
see means electrical brain picture or in
other words mapping out the electrical
activity in the brain so how we're going
to do that well first I'll go over
exactly what we're trying to measure
followed by what we're going to use to
measure it here's Bob badly drawn
stickman if we color from Bob's skull
and take a slice through his brain we
can look to the source of the electrical
activity in the cerebral cortex there
are specialized neurons could eat the
core pyramidal cells some of them are
relatively large and arranged parallel
to each other perpendicular to the
surface of the brain when action
potentials propagate along neurons local
currents are produced outside of the
cell which facilitate propagation of the
signal along the neuro
however these currents are too small to
be detected by EEG and the axons are
arranged randomly so many of the
currents cancel each other out but there
are other sources of current in neurons
at the synapse between two neurons
neurotransmitter moves across the
synaptic cleft and binds to the
postsynaptic membrane
this causes ion channels to open in a
membrane and positively charged ions
flow into the cell with the positive
ions rushing into the cell the
extracellular space around the neuron
becomes negatively charged this is shown
in orange on the diagram and is referred
to as the sink in a distant part of the
neuro the ions eventually leave the cell
and this outward flow of positive ions
leaves the extracellular space
positively charged this is shown in blue
on the diagram and is referred to as the
source the combination of these two
related processes clearly forms an
electrical dipole between different
parts of the neuron
however the dipole from a single neuron
is very small and there is a thick skull
as well as other layers of soft tissues
that pass through so individually they
are undetectable luckily as mentioned
earlier there are so many pyramidal
cells in this layer of the brain
all aligned parallel to each other and
often many of these cells are stimulated
at the same time therefore the
individually small dipoles some eight to
form a dipole which is detectable
outside the head as we can see as we can
see from the diagram if we place
electrodes on the surface of the scalp
there is a deflection in the voltage
signal compared to a reference so we
know we're measuring how do we detect
the signals seeing as we're trying to
record an electrical signal it makes
sense to use electrodes the electrodes
are placed on a scalp at very specific
locations this diagram shows the 10-20
system of electrode placement the
numbers refer to the distance from
certain reference points on the head to
ensure the placement is consistent
across different studies and this is
what it looks like when all the
electrodes are in place so now we've got
all the electrodes in place we need to
start collecting signals the problem is
when we compare them to the most obvious
way would be choosing arbitrary common
reference the electrodes signal is fed
into a differential amplifier with a
reference electrode common to each eg
signal this technique is useful and then
it should reveal the true nature and
amplitude of the signal however in
reality the reference is often active
and the distance between the electrodes
can allow interference to obscure the
signal another approach is to use
bipolar electrodes for this method each
electrode is connected to an amplifier
with the adjacent electrode this method
allows much more accurate localization
of the signal however it also distorts
the true signal and potentially permits
signals of opposing phase to cancel each
other out and be lost a third and final
approach which is commonly used is an
average reference each electrode is
passed into an amplifier along with a
signal which is an average of all the
electrodes currently being measured this
has the benefit of providing an almost
constant reference signal but allowing
us to measure the amplitude of signal as
well as negating much of the
interference so here's an example of an
EEG trace each line represents the
difference between that electrode and
the average of all the electorate's
being measured
now as you can probably guess this trace
isn't ideal
this sharp peak convicted of epileptic
events and this moves us on to the
clinically important question which is
what is the EEG shown when looking at
the EEG trace now generally a few
different types of waves characterized
by their frequency alpha waves to
forgive a frequency of 8 to 13 Hertz and
it's seen in adults at rest with eyes
closed and relaxed beta waves are higher
frequency and they are seen commonly in
alert awake adult theta waves lower
frequency and abnormal in adults who are
awake but normal during sleep and in
children delta waves are very low
frequency less than 4 hertz and they're
only normal in deep sleep and in young
babies but the most striking types of
waveforms are those seen in epilepsy
epilepsy is a neurological condition
defined by a sudden recurrent episodes
of sensory disturbance or convulsion
these events are usually linked with
abnormal electrical activity in the
brain and the most common use of the EEG
is in the diagnosis of epilepsy as you
can see there is a distinct type of wave
here known as spike and wave which is
not seen in healthy patients now the
examples they are shown clearly for
illustration purposes in reality
interpreting in EEG is a skill which
takes many years to affect thank you for
listening